<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "../schema/tei_ms_repertorium.dtd">
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <!--Irina Kuzidova; Dilyana Radoslavova--><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Rila Panegyrikon, 4/8 (61), Rila Monastrery, 1479.</title><author>Irina Kuzidova</author><author>Dilyana Radoslavova</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Institute of Literature</publisher><pubPlace>Sofia</pubPlace><date>2013.</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Printed catalogues.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language><language ident="bg">Bulgarian</language></langUsage><textClass><keywords scheme="Repertorium"><list><item>Panegyrikon</item><item>Panegyrical works</item><item>Hagiography</item><item>Vladislav the Grammarian</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><msDesc><msIdentifier><msName type="general">Panegyrikon; </msName><msName type="individual">Rila Panegyrikon.</msName><country>Bulgaria,</country><settlement>Rila,</settlement><repository>Rila Monastrery,</repository><idno type="shelfmark">4/8 (61),</idno><idno type="catalogue">130.</idno><note><listBibl><bibl><ref>Своден каталог: 131; </ref><ref>Христова 1996: 64-109.
                                </ref></bibl></listBibl></note></msIdentifier><physDesc><objectDesc form="codex"><supportDesc material="paper"><support><material>Paper.</material></support><extent>740 ff. approximately.</extent></supportDesc></objectDesc><decoDesc><p>The titles and the initials are in red. The small number of headpieces
                            are coloured in gold, ochre, green, blue, red.</p></decoDesc></physDesc><scribeDesc xmlns="http://www.ilit.bas.bg/repertorium/ns/3.0"><scribe><name xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Vladislav the Grammarian.</name><scriptDesc script="cyrs"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Middle calligraphic
                                semi-uncial.</p></scriptDesc><scribeLang><orthography><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Resava orthography with a lot
                                    of diacritical signs.</p></orthography></scribeLang></scribe></scribeDesc><msContents><summary>The miscellany contains homilies of St. John Chrysostom, Cyril of
                        Jerusalem, Atanasios of Alexandria, Gregory of Neo Caesarea, Basil of
                        Seleucia, Simeon Metaphrastes, patriarch Germanos I, etc. Apart from that
                        the Panegyrikon the MS contains interesting texts of Bulgarian and Balkan
                        Slavic literacy, such as some works of Gregory Tsamblak (Enkomion on St.
                        Demetrios of Thessaloniki and the Life of Stefan of Dečani), and works of
                        patriarch Euthymios of Tărnovo (Enkomion on SS. Constantine and Helena,
                        Enkomion on Kiriakia the Martyress, Letter to Nicodemos of Tismana, Letter
                        to Cyprianos and Letter to Antymos, archbishop of Ugro-Walachia, the Life of
                        St. John of Rila supplemented by the autograph of the so-called Rila story,
                        describing the translation of the saint's relics from Tărnovo to Rila
                        monastery. The Translatio contains a detailed account on the historical
                        circumstances preceding the event: the reestablishment of Rila monastery,
                        the battle of Čirmen (1371), the role of the widowed sultan wife Mariya
                        Branković, etc. The Rila story is critically published by Христова 1996:
                        165-177. Vladislav the Grammarian added yet another text about the Rila
                        hermit - The life with a small enkomion on St. John of Rila by Demetrios
                        Kantakouzenos. There are included two more vitae created in the 14th c. -
                        Life of St. Gregory Sinaites and Life of St. Theodosios of Tărnovo by
                        Patriarch Kallistos. Two texts are devoted to the holy brothers Cyril and
                        Methodios - Life of St. Constantine-Cyril the Philosopher and the Enkomion
                        on St. Cyril and St. Methodios. Among the text preserved in a sole copy is
                        the Enkomion on St. Philothea Temniška by Joasaph of Bdin. Thanks to its
                        specific contents the Panegyrikon is often described as a unique anthology
                        of rare translations of Byzantine works and Old and Middle Bulgarian
                        original texts.</summary></msContents><history><origin><origDate>1479.</origDate></origin></history><additional><listBibl><bibl><ref>Христова 1996: 64-109.</ref></bibl></listBibl></additional></msDesc></body></text></TEI>